<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An abstract, almost verbatim (with some necessarie addition,) of The customers apologie, written 18. yeares ago, to shew their distresse in the out-ports, aswell through want of maintenance and meanes to beare out their seruice, as countenance and credit in regard of others</title>
            <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1617</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S452</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22439483</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22439483</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25536</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07551)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25536)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1754:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An abstract, almost verbatim (with some necessarie addition,) of The customers apologie, written 18. yeares ago, to shew their distresse in the out-ports, aswell through want of maintenance and meanes to beare out their seruice, as countenance and credit in regard of others</title>
                  <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
                  <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627? Customer's apology.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Jaggard?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1617?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Tho. Milles.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Staple system --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="abstract">
            <pb facs="tcp:25536:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25536:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>An Abſtract, almoſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbatim (with ſome Neceſſarie Addition,) of the
<hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers APOLOGIE, written 18. yeares ago, to ſhew their Diſtreſſe in the Out-ports, aſwell</hi> through want of <hi>Maintenance</hi> and Meanes to beare out their Seruice; as <hi>Countenance</hi> and Credit in regard of Others.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ Now, ſee what hath bene ſaid, and ſo haſt to an End.</head>
            <p>The PRINCE (as aforeſaide) is iuſtly offended, and the Merchant likewiſe hath laide downe his Griefes. Theſe are the foure ſorts of Officers that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on Cuſtome-cauſes: namely, CVSTOMERS, SERCHERS, COMP<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TROLLERS, &amp; SVPERVISORS: amongſt whom, if any complain, theſe laſt haue no Reaſon to looke to be pittied. For that, obtruding themſelues in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other mens work, and vndertaking a taske exceeding their skil; as Men in a maze they ſtriu'd to go forward, and in dooing leſſe then Nothing, woulde theme to do all. Like ignorant auſtere Huiſhers that know no Rules to teach by but beating the Schollers.</p>
            <p>But by way of <hi>Parentheſis.</hi> Let this be worth the noting. How generally iuſt as conſequently true, theſe ancient Rules of Art, and Aſſertions of Reaſon continue and ſtand, namely, <hi>Quàm fruſtra ſit per plures quod fieri debet per pauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ores.</hi> And <hi>Inſtitutio ab initio invtilis, ex poſt facto nunquam convaleſcit.</hi> For, as theſe <hi>Superviſors</hi> doubting at the firſt the skill and good abearing of thoſe they ſought to vſe, and were to put in truſt: and ſeeing the weake foundation of
<hi>Comptrollers</hi> before them to be but <hi>Actum agere,</hi> and eaſily out-fac;t: by their new Acceſſe, the Seruice grew ſo violent, ſo intricate, and withall ſo out of Order; that the <hi>Serchers,</hi> who by office as they haue the beſt meanes to attend vpon Trafficke, ſo they ſhould by Duty depend vppon the <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with them at leaſt; leaue them to wilde Company and vnquiet Cuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and ſwaruing with the ballaſt inquire out the neereſt way to their own priuate profite.</p>
            <p>In which Diſtreſſe, the Cuſtomers in diſpleaſure with the PRINCE; in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace with the world, in the midſt of a hungry, lawleſſe, ignorant &amp; wilful kind of Men, obtruded vpon them by ialouſie and miſconceite, that like defectiue <hi>Heteroclytes</hi> wrangle as it were with the very Rules of Grammer; pittying the Merchant in regard of his Traffick; ſilently bemoan themſelues in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
            <p>That the meanes to enable them to performe their Duties, aſwell <hi>Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> as
<hi>Countenance,</hi> are ſo with-held from them, that leauing the worlde and all preferments by it, to ſerue at the <hi>Altar,</hi> they are not thought woorthie to breath and liue thereby, Their Scruice being euery way like the Bricke-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Egypt, who wanting meanes to do their Taske, had ydle Taske-may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to ouer-ſee but what they wrought, whoſe Credites had no being, but in their Diſgrace.</p>
            <p>That the Law it ſelfe, ſo good and iuſt in generall,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ialouſie</hi> and <hi>Suſpition</hi> out of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious zeale to <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and
<hi>Trafficke,</hi> haue ignorantly in all ages ſo incenſed <hi>PARLEMENTS</hi> againſt
<hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> (without diſtinguiſhing the <hi>Out ports</hi> from <hi>London</hi>) that of Free-men borne, like Bondſlaues, they are beaten to all workes, with theyr hands tide behinde them, and truſted with Nothing.</note> is made hurtfull to the PRINCE in their publique Functions, and iniurious to themſelues in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate Callings. For that whereunto they becom preciſely ſworn at their Ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſsions, namely, the aduancement of <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and conſequently Trafficke; the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> of all Men are forbidden by Statute, to wit, not to meddle or deale with Trafficke, and their Seruice being euery way no thankes to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, is a ſpecial Meanes of <hi>Mamtenance</hi> and <hi>Countenance</hi> to others. SIC VOS NON VOBIS
<hi>fertis Aratra Boues, nideficatis Aues,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they notwithſtanding, vnderly all Expences incident to Cuſtoms vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfully, which others neuer touch, and for only crying aime, reap thankes and Reward. For (omitting extraordinaries ere they come to their Places)
<pb facs="tcp:25536:2"/>their Bonds and Sureties for the Princes behoofe and ſubiection beſides, is an vnknowne burthen that the reſt little feele.</p>
            <p>They alſo are to hire and finde out at each Port of their charge a convent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Cuſtome-houſe (which the Prince ſhould prouide there as well as at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>) that,<note place="margin">No Cuſtomhouſes, no publick Wharſes nor Storehouſes builded by the Prince in the <hi>Out-portes,</hi> as there are at London.</note> alone beſides Seats, Tables, Shelues, and other neceſſarie thinges are hard to be compaſſed vnder 4 or 5. pound. So that for example, where fiue Ports are in charge, the Head-Cuſtomer ſtands chargeable yearly for fiue Cuſtome Houſes with 25. li.</p>
            <p>At each of theſe Houſes a diſcreet and able Perſon, and of honeſt educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the
<hi>Cuſtomer</hi> is to finds for his owne indemnity, that ſtands bounde for all. Whereas Any fit the reſt,<note place="margin">The Farmers by ayming at theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions, finde it by Experience to be moſt for theer profit.</note> bee they neuer ſo vntoward. And vnto ſuch, leſſe then 100. markes <hi>per annum,</hi> (to maintaine a Family,) cannot well hee giuen: which fiue all put together, makes 400. pounds a yeare, the head Cuſtomer being but doubled according to proportion.</p>
            <p>At theſe fiue Cuſtome-houſes what is yearely ſpent in publicke, for Incke, Parchment, paper, and wax, the Cuſtomer ſupplies, which may amount ſome yeares to 8. or 10. li.</p>
            <p>Beſides the hazard of turning vp to <hi>London,</hi> and putting in of moneyes (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Traffick became farmed) by Bils and otherwiſe,<note place="margin">No Portage Money allowed
<hi>Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers,</hi> in the <hi>Out-Ports,</hi> as all Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors in <hi>Counties</hi> haue.</note> beeing allowed no Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage Money, as all Collectors els but Cuſtomers are, which the Reſt breake no ſleepe for.</p>
            <p>Theirs are alſo all Expences caſuall, and needefull (beſides Trauayle for their paines) about ſending or riding from Port to Port, aſwell by Letters or Directions from the Councell, L. Threſaurer, or Exchequer; as by Proceſſes and Writs, how generally ſoeuer directed vnto all.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,<note place="margin">The <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> Charge &amp; Expence in paſting Accompts.</note> they put in their Bookes (before the generall Farme) twice a yeare duly to their double charge and paines, which the others did but once with lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or none attendance, leauing ſtil the Cuſtomers ſo to abide, follow, and pay all Fees and duties, that the beſt halfe of their owne, if not two parts of three they leafte behinde them, before they came to ſee their
<hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> beeing more encombred with the Entries and writings of the Others Bookes then of their owne, which they rather inſulted on, then car'd for to mend: colouring their Doings ſtill with the Princes onely Seruice, and vrging all Extremities, cride <hi>The Moſt for the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This being the <hi>Countenance</hi> and Seruice of <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> in the
<hi>Out-Portes</hi> of this Kingdome, ſlightly runne ouer for breuities ſake, together with their charge; now ſee but their <hi>Maintenance,</hi> which alone and by it ſelfe but indifferently waighd, may helpe to excuſe them, though the time for the preſent ſeeme hopeleſſe of releefe.</p>
            <p>The Fees and Rewards ioyntly to <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> and <hi>Comptrollers</hi> (the
<hi>Searchers</hi> are allowed the moity of their Seiſures) before the generall Farme,<note place="margin">The Fees and Rewards to Cuſtomers, &amp;c. in the Out-Ports allowed by the <hi>Prince.</hi>
               </note> amounted to the ſum of 1240, li. little vnder or ouer: whereof the <hi>Comptrollers</hi> had 340. &amp; the remainder being 900. ſerud the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> among them. This 900. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into three parts (as aboueſaide) two beeing ſpent in attending, clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and paſſing of Accompts, the remainder 300. is the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> onely, to maintaine both them and theyrs, and recompence their Bondage, beeing leſſe then that <hi>Comptrollers</hi> haue with all freedome and eaſe. A Proportion odly euen, and hard to be beleeued without <hi>Experience,</hi> yet the ſame compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the late ioynt <hi>Superviſors,</hi> made a farre ſtranger reckning. For where the Head Cuſtomers beeing in number ſome 19. diuided amongeſt them but
300 li. (<hi>deductis deducendis</hi> as aboue ſaid) and that vpon Acompt to at the years end: Theſe <hi>Superviſors</hi> in number being but 4. receiued by <hi>Debentur</hi> at euerie Quarters end, 425. li. which was 1700. li. a yeare for 16. yearee together, without accompt or reckning.</p>
            <p>Theſe 4. ſuppoſing <hi>Trafficke</hi> to be ſome Eſſex cheeſe, as it ſeem'd by they Endeuours, ſurueighd Her in the <hi>Out-Ports</hi> by wilde Rats and Mice, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of the Aire, and whipt Her vp to <hi>London</hi> where now She liues confind: and left the
<hi>Cuſtomers</hi> like Beares tyde to ſtakes, ſit now for nothing but baiting &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:25536:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>beating, with the onely choiſe and freedome to ſtatue or liue by ſhifts. So that the <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> ſtill ſetuing at the <hi>Altar,</hi> and yet held vnworthy to breath and liue thereby, their fare growing ſlender, and their drinke but ſmall and ſcant, by Cockets, Entries, and ordinary Fees, (as all publicke Offices and officers haue) out of meete neceſsity and want of Employments, they dippe but their diſhes in their Neighbours Ciſternes (with good leaue &amp; liking) to quench their thirſt, and at noone tide in their Gardens crop a few of their <hi>Lockes</hi> (with their owne free conſents) to keepe them from ſtaruing: and this now addes Oyle to the fire of their Furnace, their breaths are accuſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with their ſent and poiſon the aire, though the reſt eate <hi>Onions</hi> and feed on <hi>Garlicke.</hi> So that howſoeuer in others it ſtand with right and reaſon; That, <hi>Volentibus non ſiunt iniurie,</hi> and, <hi>Quod Neceſsitas cogit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The onely motiue of this Abſtract.</note> 
               <hi>neceſsitas defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> yet in <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> of all men it becomes a great and a horrible Sin, Burglary at leaſt, complaind of now in PARLEMENTS, and that by <hi>Merchants,</hi> and thoſe of
<hi>London</hi> too</p>
            <p>As if Cuſtomers (forſooth) by <hi>Companies</hi> and <hi>Societies,</hi> did bandy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and liu'd by Decrees of their owne contriuings, neither fit nor to bee ſquared with GODS Lawes, KINGS Lawes, nor TREATISE of Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, had broken into STAPLES, prophan'd our Soueraignes MINTS, tranſported all his Load-ſtones (ordaind to draw in BVLLION) turn'd
<hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi> into a Merchandize, vndermin'd the State with <hi>Vſurie,</hi> and at Mid-night robd a CHVRCH, to keepe GOD from his <hi>Duties,</hi> and KINGS from their <hi>Rights</hi> as London Marchants do.</p>
            <p>¶ Namely,<note place="margin">The Golden Fleece the Order of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the <hi>Dukes of Burgundie,</hi> by <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wools in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </note> as if They and none but they (I meane Cuſtomers of the Out-Ports, and none but Cuſtomers, let others cleare themſelues and Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to) engroſsing all the <hi>Wools</hi> and <hi>Woolfels</hi> of the Kingdome (the wonders of the world, and ſometimes <hi>Englands</hi> glory) and ſtapling them beyond ſeas, had made them forraigne <hi>Trophees</hi> and <hi>Enſignes</hi> of our ſhame, without Exchange of BVLLION, like Merchants of the olde <hi>Haunce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Society or Company of Merchants of the <hi>Staple.</hi>
               </note> cald Marchants of the STAPLE.</p>
            <p>¶ Or, As if they and none but they, being put in truſt with the Creame as it were, and Credite of the Kingdome <hi>(Cloth)</hi> by ſtapling it beyond Seas at priuate Mart-Townes, had brought our <hi>Clothyers</hi> to diſtreſſe, our <hi>Clothes</hi> to be deſpiſed and our
<hi>Clothing</hi> vnto nothing, at leaſt nothing leſſe then <hi>Bullion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Society</hi> or <hi>Company</hi> of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-<hi>Aduenturers.</hi>
               </note> and turn'd our Cuſtomes into <hi>Vſury</hi> by <hi>Hyſteron proteron</hi> and Billes of
<hi>Intereſt</hi> which Marchants terme <hi>Exchange,</hi> as the Marchant ADVENTVRERS were larely wont to do.</p>
            <p>¶ Or, As if they (the Cuſtomers) and none but they, ſeeing Trafficke cloath'd in
<hi>Whites,</hi> feed thouſands beyond ſeas, and ſtarue more then Milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for want of worke at home, had vndertaken to draw her ſtarke naked, from the <hi>Lime-kill</hi> to the
<hi>Cole-pit,</hi> and by a new <hi>Deceptioviſus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The newe
<hi>Society</hi> or Company of <hi>March-Aduenturers.</hi>
               </note> turne Cat but in the Pan, and dye her into <hi>Motleyes,</hi> and neuer thinke of <hi>Bullion.</hi> As the New March-ADVENTVRERS do beare in hand to do.</p>
            <p>¶ Or, Laſtly and <hi>Inſtar Omnium,</hi> As if they, and none but they, the Out-Port Cuſtomers, ſeeing Trafficke heartleſſe, pulſeleſſe, and almoſt out of breath, like a horſe already tired in a weary wilde goaſe chaſe, offered to Ranke-riders to be ridden againe in poſt, without Diet, Drinke or Dreſsing,<note place="margin">The <hi>Society</hi> or Company of <hi>Eaſt-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Marchants.</hi>
               </note> had vndertaken in the <hi>Indies</hi> to barter her for Drugs or pouldre her with Pep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, or with her owne Blood turne her wholly into Mummey, without regard of Bullion. As the <hi>India</hi> Marchants do.</p>
            <p>Whereby, as in the Empire it fares with <hi>Emperors,</hi> by Popes and Popery, ſo with Chriſtian Kings and Kingdomes, by Conclaues and Societies. For, As Honor and Reuerence (the Father and Mother of MALESTY) were brought to offer Sacrifice to REMPHAM and to RIMMON, and MAIESTIES ſelfe in <hi>Emperors</hi> compeld to do Homage to their owne Popes and Vaſſals, by
<hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity</hi> and <hi>Vſury;</hi> SOVERA'IGNTY being ſtript of all her beſt Subſiſtence and ſupplements of Bullion, Money became a Marchandiſe (ordaind for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique
<pb facs="tcp:25536:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Vtility (what ere became of Honeſty) was turn'd to priuate gaine: So MAIESTY in KINGS becomes to bee ecclipſed in their Kingdomes and Coines; their SOVERAIGNTIES ſupplanted, and <hi>Bounties</hi> vndermin'd, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which in SOVERAIGNES no Subiects can be happy) at leaſt wiſe in <hi>Great-Britaine</hi> where BOVNTY now commands, and all for want of Bullion. For, as our <hi>Staples</hi> being tranſplanted, are ſtill with-held beyond Seas by ſecular <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Popery;</hi> Our Out-ports at home beeing like wiſe brought vnder by <hi>Conclaues</hi> and <hi>Societies;</hi> Our Subſidies confounded of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Poundage,</hi> aſwel as our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> by obſtinate <hi>Preciſenes,</hi> and out Trafficke as bewitcht by <hi>Auarice</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> confin'd within the Circle of the famous Port of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don (for Greatneſſe and wealth,) and there ſet to ſale <hi>au plus offrant,</hi> made apt to bee coniured: ſo Our <hi>Standarts</hi> by Degrees falling out to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, both in <hi>Number, Waights</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> and our Monies made a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe engroſt in few mens hands: all things waxt deere, our KINGS be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came weake for want of Gold and Siluer, their Subiectes poore for want of current Moneyes or Employments at leaſt, whilſt Coin it ſelfe by <hi>Vſury,</hi> which Marchants tearme <hi>Exchange,</hi> eates out induſtry in Trades; and Marchants by <hi>Monopolyes</hi> conſpire to ſtrangle Trafficke within themſelues in <hi>London,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> by her Marchants made the Box of
<hi>Pandora</hi> to ſend forth all the euils that now perplex the Land. And all for lacke of Bullion, which Merchants by their Contracts and Societies peruert, or elſe withſtand by all the means they can.</p>
            <q>O, that euer Marchants ſhould ſit ſo neere our Holme!</q>
            <p>Yet, theſe are the Perſons that defiling the waters which run down the <hi>Thames</hi> and ſlide along our Coaſts, choake all our Ports with Oaſe, beray our clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Riuers, put TRAFFICK to her ſhiftes, and by daily aſperſions fince fault with the Out ports, and accuſe the Cuſtomers, to excuſe themſelues; as if none but they were ſinners, or that London were a Sanctuary, and none but they were Saints.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>But,</hi> Hij Nigri ſunt Omnes, Hostu <hi>REX MAGNE</hi> caueto.</q>
            <p>For, Theſe are the Men and the Marchants to, that Trade-leſſe themſelues, and of no Occupations, by <hi>Companies</hi> and <hi>Societies</hi> reſiding ſtill in <hi>London,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſe all our Trades, and liue by buying and ſelling: and ſo by buying as to ſell for priuate gaine, that making Money a Marchandiſe, they raiſe all their profits ſtill from others Trades and paines, crying <hi>Lueri bonus oder eſt ex quoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet qualibet,</hi> and preferring euer <hi>Vtile</hi> before <hi>Honeſtum Qua, nul a permties ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ior vitae hominum poteſt afferri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yea, Theſe are the perſons, that to hold all men vnder, and themſelues ſtill aboue, deale wholy out of ſight, and with publicke weapons maintaining con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions for priuat wrongs, breed nothing but complaints with vnkind iarres at home, and Enuy abroad, to the endleſſe care and cumber of KINGS and COVNCELL-TABLES, and PARLEMENTS too. And all for lacke of
<hi>Staples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For,<note place="margin">Enter-lopers in England, are as <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genots</hi> in France.</note> Theſe are the Marchants and ſpeculatiue kinde of Men, that ſeuering themſelues from the Body of our Commerce, call all men <hi>Enter-lopers</hi> that are not of their Conclaues or priuate Common wealths, and liue by their Decrees, thought euery way as Catholicke and as Free-borne an they, and perhaps better Chriſtians, though not ſo Ieſuited. And wandering out of ſight, bewitch all they meete with, and were it but poſsible, woulde ſeduce the wiſe, perſwading all and euery where, that TRAFFICKE of her ſelfe is a parillous biting Beaſt, and that to bring her home againe vnto her owne Creekes and Ports, were to worry our ſheepe in <hi>Cotſal</hi> Groundes, and ſinke our ſhips on <hi>Cheuiot</hi> Hils that ſaile on <hi>Barham</hi> Downes And by a bare pretence of <hi>Order</hi> ſtill, and orderly tranſporting the
<hi>Load-ſtones</hi> of the Lande (without regard of BVLLION) as with a wodden Dagger, ſtab all they finde or heare of, that write or ſpeake of Staples, for ſeare of our <hi>Nauy,</hi> and decay of our <hi>ſhipping.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25536:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>As, if the cheriſhing of woods were the way to ruine Forreſts, and hide our Timber-Trees. Or, that the raiſing of our Hiues againe were a conſequence in reaſon to ſpil all our Hony, and ſmother all our Bees. Whereas, al Men now perceiue it, and Experience makes it plaine, though Cuſtomers holde their peace, that as our <hi>Clothyers</hi> with their <hi>Clothes</hi> (ſuch as they are) hauing loſt their home-bred STAPLES (&amp; therewithall, their Credits) are forſt to come like Pilgrimes, from <hi>Eaſt, Weſt, North,</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> to one onely
<hi>Blacke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel Hall:</hi> and there, if not againſt their Conſciences, yet at leaſt without De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion, pittifully complaming and bemoaning one another, to ſtoope to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Saint, to crouch to euery Croſſe, and run into Idolatry: ſo our <hi>Creekes</hi> in al our <hi>Coaſts,</hi> creepe now to one Riuer. All our <hi>Riuers</hi> in our Countries run now to one Port. All our
<hi>Ports</hi> about the Kingdome ioyue now to one <hi>Towne.</hi> Al our <hi>Townes</hi> in all our Shires, make nowe but one <hi>City.</hi> And all our <hi>Cities</hi> in each <hi>Prouince, Metropolitane</hi> and all, are but Suburbs as it were, to one vaſte, vnweildy and diſorderly
<hi>Babel,</hi> that out-ſwelling all proportions, and in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger like to burſt, conteſts within it ſelfe about the multitude of Buildings, which the world cals LONDON. And
<hi>London</hi> by her Marchants contracted in her ſelfe, made a wilderneſſe of Sinne, and a Forreſt of Shifts. Whereby TRAFFICK now confin'd, and euery way poſſeſt with <hi>Rats</hi> and <hi>Mice,</hi> and <hi>spirits</hi> of the ayre (of whom as of <hi>Harpies</hi> may truly be ſaid.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Triſtius haud iſtis monſtrum nec ſaeuior vlla,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peſtis &amp; ira Deum ſtygiis ſeſe extulit vndis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No Monſters like to theſe may happe, nor curſſe from God befall,</l>
               <l>Nor from the Pit of hell ariſe, to plague the Realme withal:)</l>
               <l>Is ſo become tormented both by Water and by Land,</l>
               <l>That how to helpe her now, God knowes, I do not vnderſtand.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Except it be by PARLEMENT to reſtaure again our STAPLES, that K. IAMES may finde his Bullion, as K. Edw. ſometimes did after 15. yeares experience, and ſo became moſt happy, til Marchants got the Helme againe, and Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe out-ſhot his marke, by tranſplanting that of
<hi>Kent</hi> from <hi>Cantorburie</hi> to <hi>Calays.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For as <hi>London</hi> ſeemes diſtempered now, and diſtracted in it ſelf by the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of people, and magnitude of Buildings; had it all our TEMPLES downe (as indeed it hath our <hi>Staples</hi>) that men might run on Pilgrimage to the ſhri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Saints of London; as our KING wantes his Cuſtomes, ſo GOD might ſeeke his Tythes, there or beyond ſeas, what ere became of Subſidies or Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wil-Offerings either. And what ere betide of TRAFFICK,<note place="margin">Trafficke and Shipping are relatiues.</note> alias SHIPPING for all her Marchants Orders, ſo ſeriouſly pretended; our <hi>Iuſtice Commutatiue</hi> might take her Enter-Iopers, enquire for true <hi>Religion,</hi> learne the way to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and take her leaue of LONDON, and ENGLAND too, for all our Faires and Markets, or priuate Pariſh Churches.</p>
            <p>On whoſe behalfe therefore, without ſelfe or ſide Reſpects, though my Faith be but fraile, my ſpirits wel-nie ſpent, and my Credite almoſt gone, yet doth my vow compell me ſtil to doe my beſt endeuour, and to wiſh and pray for Staples as heartily as I can, for the Conſequences ſake. But in the mean ſeaſon, and as the caſe now ſtands, ſeeing all make loue to <hi>Tributes</hi> ſtill,<note place="margin">Al ſeeke to farme Trafficke, in one thing or other, but care not for <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomers.</hi>
               </note> and catch our Functions from vs, both <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Low, Rich</hi> and <hi>Poore, Noble</hi> and <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble,</hi> becauſe their Leſſons ſpell <hi>Siluer</hi> and <hi>Gold,</hi> and yet our Names they ſhun. Let <hi>Ialouſie</hi> bee cald for now, and let <hi>Impudency</hi> ſmell what
<hi>Ignorance</hi> hath gained, and <hi>Extremity</hi> reformed in all the Schooles of
<hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> by ſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling well the Letters, but miſtaking the purpoſe of a witty PREVY COVN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CELLOR, that ſomtimes gaue aduice in this very caſe of Ours.<note place="margin">Sir Tho: Moores Epigram, <hi>de Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torib. abolend.</hi>
               </note> Viz.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sectile ne tetros porrum tibi ſpiret odores,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Portinus a porre fac mibi cepe vores, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25536:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>In Engliſh thus:</l>
                  <l>Leaſt eating<note n="1" place="margin">CVSTOMERS.</note> LEEKES (ſaith he) ſhould make thy breath to ſmell,</l>
                  <l>Take<note n="2" place="margin">COMPTROLLERS.</note> ONIONS ſtrong, that ſent will ſoone allay:</l>
                  <l>And if thereby the ſauour ſeeme to excell,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note n="3" place="margin">SVPERVISORS.</note>GARLICKE be ſure will driue them both away.</l>
                  <l>But if the naſty ſmell of <hi>Garlicke</hi> ſtay,</l>
                  <l>What helpes vs then?<note n="4" place="margin">FARMERS.</note> TOBACCO? No: but at a word I thinke,</l>
                  <l>There are that dare to<note n="5" place="margin">Searching, ſharking, vndertaking, raking Waiters, at the Waters ſide.</note> VNDERTAKE, and make a viler ſtinke.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe as the Obloquies of Cuſtomers and Cuſtome-houſes ſcandals, fiſh ſtill in pudled waters, and calling all things Cuſtomes, that indeede are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, prophane the Name of KINGS. Theſe hunt and ferret Trafficke in euery Porte and Creeke, and ſo tumble and torment her as it were by Commiſſion, to keepe her ſtill from reſt: that Shee her ſelfe complaines now, aſwel within the Out-ports, as at euery gate of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Sicut Bufo Crati,</l>
               <l>Maledicti tot Dominati.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Whilſt the Out-port-Cuſtomers, being ſet to ſweepe the Houſes that others ſtill defile, and left to feede on Thiſtles, or to liue by the aire; out of hart, out of Friends, out of Credite and Requeſt, dare finde fault with nothing, but make Signes with their Pens, and write onely,
<q>ADSIT REGVLA.</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho: Milles.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25536:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25536:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25536:5"/>
            <trailer>END</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
